<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
 Copyright 2001-2005 The Apache Software Foundation.

 Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License")
 you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
 You may obtain a copy of the License at

     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 limitations under the License.
-->

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Torque Tutorial</title>
    <author email="pete-apache-dev@kazmier.com">Pete Kazmier</author>
    <author email="seade@backstagetech.com.au">Scott Eade</author>
    <author email="fischer@seitenbau.de">Thomas Fischer</author>
  </properties>
  <body>

<section name="About this Tutorial">

<p>
  This tutorial is intended to give first-time users an
  introduction to using Torque, an object-relational tool.
</p>

<p>
  This will include how to obtain the Torque distribution,
  setting up a database, and writing a sample application
  to demonstrate the power of Torque.  The tutorial is not
  meant to be an exhaustive introduction to Torque, please
  refer to the documentation on the
  <a href="../">Torque homepage</a> for more
  detailed information.
</p>

<p>
  In this tutorial, it is assumed that you have experience 
  in programming in Java, and that you have some experience
  using JDBC (e.g. you should know what a jdbc driver and a
  connection URL is).
  Although <a href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven</a> 
  is heavily used in this tutorial, it is not assumed that 
  you have any experience in using it.
</p>

<p>
  For each step in the tutorial, user comments are available 
  in the
  <a href="http://wiki.apache.org/db-torque/">Torque Wiki</a>,
  see the links at the bottom of each page.
  If you had difficulties with a particular step and found
  a solution, please write it up and add it to the corresponding
  wiki page for each step.
</p>

<p>
  If you are using Torque for the first time, you should 
  stick very closely to the example provided in the Tutorial,
  and get the sample application running as is. 
  If you play around, there are quite a few places where 
  things can go wrong, and is not always clear why they go wrong.
  Errors are much easier to find when you can pinpoint
  the source of the error by 
  &quot;Ok, it went wrong when I changed foo&quot;.<br />
  Once you got a running example, you can (and should) still 
  play around to see whether Torque can satisfy your particular 
  needs.
</p>

<p>
  The example used throughout this tutorial is based on an
  email sent to the turbine-user mailing list by 
  Steven F. Davis called
  <a href="http://mail-archives.apache.org/mod_mbox/jakarta-turbine-user/200109.mbox/%3cBCAC8D6E905D234C84A49D1524A19CD1044FF7@bemail.BEDOMAIN.BEAP.COM%3e">
  torque outside turbine - detailed example (long)</a>.
  It has subsequently been updated for Turbine 3.1 which
  separates the <a href="../generator/">generator</a> from
  the <a href="../">runtime</a> and provides a 
  <a href="../maven-plugin/">maven-plugin</a> for executing
  the generator using <a href="http://maven.apache.org/">
  Maven</a>.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Where to next">

<p>
  First we will look at <a href="step1.html">Installing Maven and the Torque Maven Plugin</a>.
</p>

</section>

<section name="User Comments">
  <a href="http://wiki.apache.org/db-torque/TutorialUserComments">User comments</a>
  for the tutorial as a whole and this page  
</section>

  </body>
</document>

