<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Torque Tutorial</title>
    <author email="pete-apache-dev@kazmier.com">Pete Kazmier</author>
    <author email="seade@backstagetech.com.au">Scott Eade</author>
    <author email="fischer@seitenbau.de">Thomas Fischer</author>
 </properties>
  <body>

<section name="Step 1: Obtaining the Torque Distribution">

<p>
  First of all, note that Torque is divided into three parts.
  <ul>
    <li>
      The generator generates your persistence classes from an xml
      description of the database. It also generates and executes
      sql scripts to create all the necessary tables, constraints etc. 
      in your database.
    </li>
    <li>
      The maven plugin integrates the generator into 
      <a href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven</a>, a software 
      project management tool.
    </li>
    <li>
      The runtime has to be included in your projects for the generated classes
      to work properly.
    </li>
  </ul>
  For this tutorial, we will be using the maven plugin for Torque 3.2.x 
  (which will silently invoke the generator) to
  generate our object model classes and the Torque 3.2.x runtime for our
  application that makes use of the generated classes.
</p>

<p>
  If you have not already done so, download and install 
  <a href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven</a>.  You then need to obtain the 
  Torque maven plugin.  The <a href="../maven-howto.html">Maven Howto</a> 
  includes details of how to build the maven plugin from source, but you can 
  easily install a binary distribution thus:
</p>

<source><![CDATA[
maven plugin:download -DartifactId=maven-torque-plugin -DgroupId=torque -Dversion=3.2-rc1
]]></source>

<p>
  At runtime the generated object model classes need access to the Torque 
  runtime distribution and associated libraries - these are available from the
  <a href="http://db.apache.org/torque/download.html">
  Downloads page</a> (the file to download is torque-3.2-rc1.tar.gz or 
  torque-3.2-rc1.zip, depending on your development platform).  We will cover
  what to do with this file in a later step.
</p>

<p>
  If you are using the maven plugin, you do not need to download the generator 
  separately. The maven plugin will download the needed resources.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Where to next">

<p>
  Next we will look at <a href="step2.html">Configuring Torque</a>.
</p>

</section>

  </body>
</document>
